Historical Reference, University; Collection ua950.008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University Historical Reference Collection
1871-1995
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua950.008
2.31 cubic ft.
This collection is made up of reference material related to the history of the University at Albany and its earlier iterations.
Administrative History
There have been many different histories of the New York State Normal School, The New York State Normal College, The New York State College for Teachers, and the State University of New York at Albany. As early as 1884 there was a history of the New York State Normal School published. Since then there has been expanions to that hsitory, as well as original works focusing on the more recent iterations of the School.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of various publications focusing on the history of the New York Satte Normal School, New York State Normal College, New York State College for Teachers, and the State University of New York at Albany. These histories cover a range of dates related to the institutions. It includes publications from the 1880's up to the book "Tradition of Excellence: 1844 to 1994" by Kandell A. Birr.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection is arranged in chronological order.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Reference Books; Education--History; UAlbany Reference Collections
- Catalogue of the Graduates of the State Normal School, 1871 (Volume 1)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal School at Albany, 1884 (Volume 2)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal School at Albany, 1884 (Volume 3)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal School at Albany, 1884 (Volume 4)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal School at Albany, 1884 (Volume 5)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal School at Albany, 1888 (Volume 6)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal School at Albany, 1888 (Volume 7)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal School at Albany, 1888 (Volume 8)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal School at Albany, 1894 (Volume 9)
- A Historical Sketch of the State Normal College at Albany, 1918 (Volume 10)
- New York State College for Teachers: Master's Theses Directory 1914-1931 (Volume 11)
- New York State College for Teachers: Master's Theses Directory 1933-1937, 1938 (Volume 12)
- College of the Empire State: A Centennial History, 1944 (Volume 13)
- A Liberal arts in the Curricula for the Preparation of Teachers, 1967 (Volume 14)
- Short History of the Graduate School of Public Affairs, 1971 (Volume 15)
- Establishment of the School of criminal Justice, 1976 (Volume 16)
- Center and Institutes: A Directory, 1982 (Volume 17)
- State University of New York at Albany: 1844-1984 A Short History (Volume 18)
- Center and Institutes: A Directory, 1987 (Volume 19)
- Center and Institutes: A Directory, 1987 (Volume 20)
- A Draft History of the State University of New York, 1988 (Volume 21)
- Center and Institutes: A Directory, 1990 (Volume 22)
- History of the University at Albany, 1990 (Volume 23)
- A Tradition of Excellence: a Sesquicentennial Commemoration, 1994 (Volume 24)
- Tradition of Excellence, Final Draft, ca. 1994 (Volume 25)
- Tradition of Excellence, Early, longer drafts, ca. 1994 (Volume 26)
- Tradition of Excellence: The Sesquicentennial History of the University at Albany, State University of New York, 1844 to 1994 (Volume 27)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains all chapters of the published book as well as most of the photographs that it featured.
  Biographical / Historical
  The university commissioned a history to celebrate its 150th anniversary in 1994. A Tradition of Excellence was researched and written by history professor Kendall Birr and edited by Vincent Reda.
  - Chapter I: Beginnings 1844 to 1848, pages 11-24, 1994
  - Chapter II: The Normal School 1848 to 1890, pages 25-44, 1994
  - Chapter III From Normal School to College for Teachers 1890 to 1915, pages 45-61, 1994
  - Chapter IV: The College for Teachers in Wars and Depression 1915 to 1945, pages 63-87, 1994
  - Chapter V: The Apogee of Teacher Education, pages 93-117, 1994
  - Chapter VI: Creating a University in the 1960s, pages 118-153, 1994
  - Chapter VII: Weathering a Turbulent Era 1969 to 1976, pages 155-175, 1994
  - Chapter VIII: The Emgergence of a Mature Public Research University 1976 to 1994, pages 177-217
    - Tradition of Excellence Photographs: Chapters 1-3, 1994 (Volume 28)
      - Dust Jacket: Stained Glass Window, Undated
      - Endsheet: Illustration of the Willett Street Building (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 2 and 3: Class of 1879 Group Photograph
      - Page 4: Geology Class Trip to Van Rensselaer Bank Moraine (photograph missing), 1906
      - Page 6: Domestic Science Faculty (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 9: President-elect Cleveland at the Closing Exercises of the State Normal School, 1885 January 27
      - Page 10: David Perkins Page, First Principal of the Normal School, Undated
      - Page 12: Gideon Hawley, Undated
      - Page 13 A-Top: Alonzo Potter, Member of the First Executive Committee, Undated
      - Page 13 B-Bottom: Horace Mann, Educational Reformer, Undated
      - Page 14: Photograph of the Final Legislation establishing the Normal School (photo missing), Undated
      - Page 15: Friend Humphrey; Mayor of Albany 1834-1845, 1849-1850, Undated
      - Page 16: Cover of the 1847 Annual Register and Circular of the State Normal School, Undated
      - Page 17: William Franklin Phelps, '45; Founder of Model School, Undated
      - Page 19: Daily Class Schedule for Winter 1847-1848. (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 20: Oldest Extant Diploma for George H. Dunham, 1847
      - Page 21: Phoebe Ann Barnard, '47, Undated
      - Page 22: David Perkins Page search itinerary for potential students, 1845, Undated
      - Page 24: A group of women students living in an Elm Street Boarding House (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 26: Faculty Photo, including Principal George R. Perkins front row center (photograph missing), ca. 1850
      - Page 27: First permanent home of the Normal School constructed in 1849 at Lodge and Howard Streets (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 28 A-Top: Samuel B. Woolworth, Principal 1852-1856, Undated
      - Page 28 B-Bottom: David A. Cochran, Principal 1856-1864, Undated
      - Page 29 A-Top: Oliver Arey, Principal 1864-1867, Undated
      - Page 29 B-Bottom: Joseph Alden, President 1867-1882 (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 30: William Jones '68, Professor of Mathematics 1869-1890, First Principal of Model School, 1890, Undated
      - Page 31: Kate Stoneman, '66; New York suffragist and first women to pass the bar exam in New York State, Undated
      - Page 32 A-Middle Right: Rodney G. Kimball; Mathematics Professor and 44th NY Volunteers Captain, Undated
      - Page 32 B-Top Right: Albert N. Husted, '55; Mathematics Professor and Lt. and later Cpt. in 44th NY Volunteer Company, Undated
      - Page 32 C-Bottom Left: Thompson Barrich, '61; Civil War Solider, Undated
      - Page 32 D-Bottom Middle: J. Oscar Blakely, '62; Civil War Soldier, Undated
      - Page 32 E-Bottom Right: Andress B. Hull, '62 Civil War Captain, Undated
      - Page 34 A-Left: Caroline G. Parker; Normal School Student and Sister of Ely S. Parker, Undated
      - Page 34 B-Right: Nicholson Henry Parker, Normal School Student and Interpreter for the Iroquois Nation, Undated
      - Page 35 A-Top: Senzaburo Kodzu, '77: First International Student, Undated
      - Page 35 B-Bottom: Edward B. Horton, '86, 1944
      - Page 36 A-Left: Cover of the Program for the Closing Exercises of the Philomathean Society, 1882 June 7
      - Page 36 B-Right: Program for the Gentlemen's Literary Society (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 37: Autograph Books and Photo Albums from the 1850s through the 1870s, Undated
      - Page 38: Letter from the women faculty praising President Alden's equal pay measures (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 39 A-Left: Mary McClellan, '68; teacher of English Grammar and History at the Normal School, Undated
      - Page 39 B-Bottom: Mary F. Hyde, '69; Teacher of Arithmetic, Geometry and Rhetoric, Undated
      - Page 40: Albert N. Husted later in life., Undated
      - Page 41 A-Top: The Class of 1888 outside the Willett Street Building (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 41 B-Bottom: Sketch of the Willett Street Building (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 42: The Chapel/Assembly Hall of the Willett Street Building with the Alumni Memorial Window in background (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 43 A-Top: Edward P. Waterbury, President 1882-1889. (photograph missing), Undated
      - Page 43 B-Bottom: Jenny Wornham Wickham, '86, Undated
      - Page 44: The Echo Editorial Board, 1904
      - Page 45: Front Cover of Vol. 16 No. 2 of The Echo, 1907 October
      - Page 46: Principal Anna Pierce, '84 and Aurelia Hyde, '95 with Model Primary School Students in Washington Park, Undated
      - Page 47 A-Top: William J. Milne; President 1889-1914, Undated
      - Page 47 B-Bottom: Andrew Draper; First New York Commissioner of Education, Undated
      - Page 48: Ruins of the Willett Street Building after it was gutted by fire., 1906 January 9
      - Page 49: Class of 1907 outside the Trinity Methodist Church (photograph missing)
      - Page 50: Professor Wetmore's Natural Sciences Laboratory in the Willett Street Building, Undated
      - Page 51: Drawing class on the new campus, 1911
      - Page 52: Delta Omega Sorority, 1900
      - Page 53 A-Top: Members of the Phi Delta Fraternity (photograph missing), 1900
      - Page 53 B-Bottom: Members of the Psi Gamma Sorority (photograph missing), 1900
      - Page 54 A-Top: William B. Aspinwall, '00, Undated
      - Page 54 B-Bottom: M. Harriet Bishop, Undated
      - Page 55 A-Top: State Normal College Varsity Baseball Team, 1900
      - Page 55 B-Bottom: Normal College students in the backyard of their boarding house at 290 Lark Street (photograph missing), 1901
      - Page 56: Illustration of the Husted, Draper and Hawley buildings on the downtown campus, 1909
      - Page 57 A-Top: State Normal College Men's Basketball Team, 1911
      - Page 57 B-Bottom: State Normal College Women's Basketball Team, 1911
      - Page 58: Student cast from the 1911 production of The Rivals
      - Page 59 A-Top Middle: Aurelia Hyde, '95; first grade teacher 1895-1907, Undated
      - Page 59 B-Top Right: Bertha Brimmer, '00, Undated
      - Page 59 C-Bottom Right: Anna Boocheever de Beer, '12, Undated
      - Page 61: Members of the Class of 1911 at their fifth reunion in 1916
  - Tradition of Excellence Photographs: Chapters 4-5, 1994 (Volume 29)
    - Page 62: The Faculty in 1919. The front row (l to r): David Hutchinson (Government), Leonard Wood Richardson (Greek and Latin), Dean Anna E. Pierce, Dean Harland Hoyt Horner, President Abram Brubacher, John Sayles (principal of Milne), Adna Wood Risley (History), Clifford Ambrose Woodward (Biology).
    - Page 64 A-Top: A Student Army Training Corp unit on campus. (photograph missing), 1918
    - Page 64 B-Bottom: Gertrude C. Valentine, a Greek and Latin Instructor killed in an automobile accident in France in 1919 while serving in the YWCA. (photograph missing), Undated
    - Page 65 A-Top: Edward Eldred Potter, '18, a member of the Army Air Corps, was another of the College's wartime casualties. He later gave his name to a prominent local fraternity., Undated
    - Page 65 B-Bottom: Students engaged in Red Cross War Work., Undated
    - Page 66 A-Top: Myskania, which founded the Student Association in 1921. Myskania continued to exist as the Student Judiciary until the 1970s., 1918
    - Page 66 B-Bottom: The Class of 1918 at Moving-Up Day in 1917. (photograph missing)
    - Page 67 A-Top: A group of women students have a "Freshman Party at '25," from the scrapbook of Dorothy Graninger, '16., ca. 1916
    - Page 67 B-Bottom: A group of male students seated on the steps of their boarding house., ca. 1917
    - Page 68 A-Top: Students in the Industrial Arts Program., 1915
    - Page 68 B-Bottom: Women's Gymnastics Class., 1915
    - Page 69 A-Top: Leanard Anderson Blue, first Dean of the College., 1916
    - Page 69 B-Bottom: Edna Merrit, '18, was one of many Albany graduates who became missionaries. She is pictured here in 1936 with the junior high graduating class at Sienyu in Fukien, China.
    - Page 70: History Professor Adna Wood Risley in class circa 1922. Professor Risley is said to have owned the first automobile in Albany.
    - Page 71 A-Top: Panoramic view of campus highlighting 1929 addition of (l-r) Milne, Page and Richardson Halls., Undated
    - Page 71 B-Bottom: Class of 1920 and 1922 at a Halloween Party.
    - Page 72: Women's Horseback Riding Team., 1923
    - Page 73 A-Top: Men's Varsity Football Team., 1922
    - Page 73 B-Bottom: Men's Tennis Team., 1929
    - Page 74: Syddum Hall in its second location in Englewood Place., Undated
    - Page 75 A-Top: Women dancing in the parlor of Newman Hall at 741 Madison Avenue., ca. 1942
    - Page 75 B-Bottom: The Chi Sigma Theta Sorority House on State Street., Undated
    - Page 76 A-Top: The Menorah Society, a Jewish religious group founded in 1923., 1924
    - Page 76 B-Bottom: A homecoming Dormitory Fund float., Undated
    - Page 77 A-Top: Portrait of Anna Eloise Pierce., Undated
    - Page 77 B-Bottom: "Dean Pierce's Idea of Sigma Nu Kappa House," a cartoon from the Psi Gamma Sorority publication The Pretzel., 1924
    - Page 78 A-Top: The Class of 1931 during their freshman year., 1928
    - Page 78 B-Bottom: "A Day at Ken Miller's farm, during which the Potter Club may or may not have been born.", ca. 1931
    - Page 79 A-Center: Gladys Newell, '30; a social studies teacher for 40 years and the President of the New York State Teachers' Association in 1966., Undated
    - Page 79 B-Top Right: Arvid Burke, '28; served for years as director of studies for the New York State Teachers' Association and completed his career as a faculty member from 1960 to 1971 in Albany's School of Education., Undated
    - Page 79 C-Bottom Right: Paul Bulger, '36; became a distinguished educator, serving as an Assistant Commissioner of Education in New York and as President of the State University College at Buffalo., Undated
    - Page 80: Members of the Class of 1933 at their first reunion June 16, 1934., 1934 June 16
    - Page 81: Agnes Futterer, Undated
    - Page 82 A-Top: K. Leroy Irvis, '38; became Democratic Leader and speaker of the Pennsylvania House of Representatives. He received an honorary degree from Albany in 1986 for his achievements. (photograph missing), Undated
    - Page 82 B-Bottom: Dorothy Griffin Griffin, '34. became a businesswoman and president of the Varflex Corporation in Rome, New York., Undated
    - Page 83: Members of the Class of '35 clowning around for the camera., Undated
    - Page 84: Abram Brubacher, Undated
    - Page 85 A-Top Left: Dean Milton Nelson, Undated
    - Page 85 B-Top Middle: Faculty member Ruth Hutchins (art), Undated
    - Page 85 C-Top Right: Faculty member Harry Birchenough (math), Undated
    - Page 85 D-Middle Center: Faculty member Robert Frederick (education), Undated
    - Page 85 E-Middle Right: Faculty member Mattie Green (physician), Undated
    - Page 86: A field trip in the Pine Bush with Dr. Gertrude Douglas., ca. 1941
    - Page 87 A-Left: The charter members of the Inter-Group Council., 1944
    - Page 87 B-Right: John Sayles, who succeeded Brubacher as Acting President in 1939 and President in 1941., 1944
    - Page 88 A-Left: Political Scientist Robert Rienow served in the Army and later served for many years as an Officer in the New York National Guard., Undated
    - Page 88 B-Right: Thurston T. Paul, '35, in his service uniform., Undated
    - Page 89 A-Top Left: Lt. Zollie Privett in the cockpit of his Tenth Air Force plane., Undated
    - Page 89 B-Bottom Left: Jack Smith, '43, later a long-time physics professor at Albany, was present at the explosion of the first atomic bomb in New Mexico in 1945., Undated
    - Page 89 C-Right: Marjorie Bishop, '42 and another alumni serving in the WAVES., Undated
    - Page 90: Kappa Beta reunion dinner to commemorate the final State College servicemen having been discharged from war service., 1946 May
    - Page 91: College centennial observation. From left to right: author John Erksine; Regent Leland Thompson; U.S. Commissioner of Education George Stoddard; Judge Newton B. VanDerzee; President John Sayles., 1944
    - Page 92: Hawley Library Reading Room., 1940
    - Page 94: Vanderzee Hall., Undated
    - Page 95: Male students playing pool in Vanderzee Hall., Undated
    - Page 96 A-Top: President Evan Revere Collins with his wife and faculty., Undated
    - Page 96 B-Bottom: President Evan R. Collins. (photo missing), Undated
    - Page 97: Oscar Lanford, member of the Chemistry Faculty and later Dean of the College (1952-1961)., Undated
    - Page 98 A-Top: Edgar Flinton, Dean of Graduate Studies., Undated
    - Page 98 B-Bottom: Ellen Stokes, Dean of Women., Undated
    - Page 99 A-Top Left: Construction of Brubacher Hall., ca. 1950
    - Page 99 B-Top Right: Governor Thomas E. Dewey speaking from the steps of Page Hall., 1950
    - Page 99 C-Bottom: Exterior of Pierce Hall and Alumni Quad Courtyard., Undated
    - Page 100 A-Top: Students in a Sayles Hall dorm room., Undated
    - Page 100 B-Bottom: Men cleaning the cafeteria in Sayles Hall. (photo missing), Undated
    - Page 101: Students gathered in the drawing room in Pierce Hall., ca. 1947
    - Page 102: The dining room at Sayles Hall., Undated
    - Page 103: A favorite activity in the 1950s and early 1960s was a visit to the Brubacher Snack Bar., Undated
    - Page 104 A-Top: Faculty member Ralph Tibbets, MA, '42 (education)., Undated
    - Page 104 B-Bottom: Faculty member Vivian Hopkins (English and comparative literature)., Undated
    - Page 105 A-Top: Faculty member Paul Pettit (English and comparative literature)., Undated
    - Page 105 B-Bottom: Faculty member Josiah Phinney (economics)., Undated
    - Page 106: Naoshi Koriyama, '54; A noted English language poet and professor at Toyo University in Japan, Koriyama was one of the first international students at Albany since the 19th Century., 1958
    - Page 107 A-Top: A chemistry laboratory., ca. 1957
    - Page 107 B-Bottom: A biology laboratory., ca. 1947
    - Page 108 A-Top: Rivalry tug-of-war., Undated
    - Page 108 B-Bottom: Freshman Camp., ca. 1950
    - Page 109 A-Top: Women's gym class in the Page Gym., 1946
    - Page 109 B-Bottom: Women's softball game., 1948
    - Page 110 A-Top: The Boulevard Café was the meeting place for the Philosophy Club., 1940
    - Page 110 B-Bottom: Christmas Formal dance, sponsored by the Inter-Sorority and Inter-Fraternity Councils, 1947
    - Page 111 A-Top: Agnes Futterer fencing with Arthur Lennig, '55, future faculty member., Undated
    - Page 111 B-Bottom: Harold Gould, '47 (photo missing), Undated
    - Page 112 A-Top: Hillel member Marvin Wayne, '49 and group advisor Rabbi Moseson, 1948
    - Page 112 B-Bottom: Dorothy De Cicco, '52, (Gamma Kappa Phi), Joan Reilly, '53 (Chi Sigma Theta), John Stevenson, '51 (Sigma Lambda) and David Wetherby, '51 (Potter Club) follow student tradition and "meet at Minnie" in Draper Hall., ca. 1951
    - Page 113: Campus Queen Audrey Koch, '50 and her court. (photo missing), 1949
    - Page 114 A-Top: Louis Wolner, '30 and Leonard E. Friedlander, '39, president of the Alumni Association, pass the torch to Sigmund Smith, president of the Class of 1956 in the annual Torchlight Ceremony.
    - Page 114 B-Bottom: Campus Day 1948: John Jennings, '49 (center) the first African-American student elected president of the Student Association (1948-1949) presents Donald Ely, '51, leader of the victorious Green Gremlins with the Campus Day Cup as Harold "Sparky" Vaugh, '50, leader of the Yellow Jackets, looks on.
    - Page 115 A-Top Left: Joseph Persico, '52. (photo missing), Undated
    - Page 115 B-Top Right: Clarence Rappleyea, '57, Undated
    - Page 115 C-Bottom Left: Harvey Milk, '51 (photo missing), Undated
    - Page 115 D-Bottom Right: Betty Duda, '59, 1963
    - Page 116 A-Left: Edith O. Wallace, '17 and first chairperson of the Division of Humanities., Undated
    - Page 116 B-Right: Cover of the Saturday Review with a glowing endorsement of the College., 1962 January 20
    - Page 117: Students passing between classes on the portico connecting Hawley to Draper. (photo missing), ca. 1955
  - Tradition of Excellence Photographs: Chapters 6-8, 1994 (Volume 30)
    - Page 118: Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller throws a shovelful of dirt on the Albany Country Club's 16th fairway to mark the ground-breaking of the new campus., 1962 August 24
    - Page 120: Students protest at the State Capitol over the imposition of tuition., 1962
    - Page 121: Rivalry Week., 1962
    - Page 122 A-Top: Quarter Century Club members Henrietta Brett, '15, Jacob Epstein, '15 and Florence Linindoll Hilton, '31 on Alumni Day., 1962
    - Page 122 B-Bottom: Dr. Arthur Collins, '48 presents Robert Steinhauer, '62 with the Agnes Futterer Award., 1962
    - Page 123: Aerial view of the Albany Country Club., ca. 1960
    - Page 124: Mayor Erastus Corning and Governor Nelson Rockefeller look over the model of the planned campus. (photograph missing), Undated
    - Page 125 A-Top Left: Aerial view of the completed Dutch Quad., ca. 1965
    - Page 125 B-Top Right: A section of pre-cast concrete is hoisted onto the Education Building., 1965 February 11
    - Page 125 C-Bottom: The Main Fountain Area and Lecture Centers under construction., 1966 March 21
    - Page 126: Walter Tisdale, a retired U.S. Army Engineer, served as the University's liaison with the architect and successfully influenced the final design of the campus., Undated
    - Page 127 A-Top: The laying of the cornerstone on Dutch Quad., Undated
    - Page 127 B-Bottom: The time capsule placed into the Dutch Quad cornerstone., Undated
    - Page 128 A-Top: The final graduation at the Downtown Campus. (photograph missing), 1965
    - Page 128 B-Bottom: Homecoming Queen Harriet Tucker., 1965
    - Page 129: Old mascot "Pierre the Ped-guin" and a new banner with the Great Dane mascot., Undated
    - Page 130: Torch Night., 1966
    - Page 131: Governor Rockefeller addresses the first graduation on the new campus. (photograph missing), 1966
    - Page 132: Dutch Quad Dining Hall., 1964
    - Page 133: Sigma Tau Beta rush., 1968
    - Page 134: The two campuses were, and still are, connected by University-operated buses., Undated
    - Page 135: State University of New York at Albany's first G.E. College Bowl team., 1966 January
    - Page 136: Webb Fiser, Vice President for Academic Affairs, Undated
    - Page 137 A-Top: Clifton C. Thorne, Vice President for Student Affairs., Undated
    - Page 137 B-Bottom: Milton Olson, Dean of Business (1962-1966), Vice President for Business (1966-1973) (photograph missing), Undated
    - Page 138 A-Top Left: Merlin Hathaway joined the staff in 1944 and oversaw the rapid expansion of physical education and intercollegiate athletics in the 1960s., Undated
    - Page 138 B-Top Right: Helen Horowitz came to Albany in 1960 in economics and became one of the most respected undergraduate teachers in the University.